Department of Justice Investigative Files on Industrial Workers of the World, Part 1 on Microfilm 5863 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Department of Justice Investigative Files on Industrial Workers of the World, Part 1 on Microfilm
1914-1976
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. Department of Justice
Industrial Workers of the World (IWW)
5863 mf
1.67 cubic feet
15 microfilm reels
Records, microfilm..
5722535
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, April 04, 2013
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, August 03, 2015
Biographical / Historical
The Industrial Workers of the World (IWW), commonly known as the Wobblies is an industrial union formed in Chicago in 1905. The IWW promotes the concept of 'One Big Union' and is considered a radical trade union, who opposes most of the policies of the American Federation of Labor. Membership does not require that one work in a represented workplace, nor does it exclude membership in another labor union. The Wobblies believe that all workers should organize as a class, not according to craft. The IWW emphasized rank- and-file organization as opposed to empowering leaders who would bargain with employers.
The biggest contribution the IWW had on the labor movement was when founded it allowed everyone to join, women, immigrants, African Americans and Asians.
As of 2005, the 100th Anniversary of its founding, the IWW had around 5,000 members.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5177 mf: Industrial Workers of the World Miscellany on Microfilm 5210: IWW Records 5210 G: IWW Graphics
United States.; Communist Party of America.; Industrial Workers of the World.; United States. Dept. of Justice.
5722535
- RG 60 - Straight Numerical File (Reel 1)
  - 0000. Industrial Workers of the World Activities in California and the Pacific Northwest. Case file 150139. Section 1. 206 pages., 1910-1916; 1 (Reel 1)
    Scope and Contents
    People: E.P. Marsh; William D. Haywood; Hiram W. Johnson; James McGill; Woodrow W. Wilson; Thomas w. Gregory; Franklin K. Lane; Charles D. Hilles; George W. Wickersham; F. W. Estabrook. Subjects: Local union and mass meeting protests against Everett, Washington, massacre of Industrial Workers of the World members; Washington State Federation of Labor; Department of Justice investigation of activities of the Industrial Workers of the World in California Oregon, Utah, and Washington; Industrial Workers of the World membership statistics and publications; Commission on Immigration and Housing of California; free speech movement in San Diego, California; Republican National Committee; protests against Industrial Workers of the World activities; free speech movement in Spokane, Washington. For pages omitted after Frame 0064, see end of Reel 1.
  - 0206. Industrial Workers of the World Activities in California and the Pacific Northwest. Case file 150139. Section 2. 145 pages., 1916-1917; 2 (Reel 1)
    People: Victor L. Berger. Subjects: Anti-war and selective service matters; Industrial Workers of the World activities in Minnesota and Wisconsin; Industrial Workers of the World publications; strikes; local union protests against Everett, Washington, massacre of Industrial Workers of the World members; Socialist party of America.
  - 0351. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case file 185354. Section 1. 208 pages., 1917-1918; 3 (Reel 1)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings; J. Edward Morgan; Alexander Berkman; Emma Goldman; Harry Weinberger; Thomas W. Gregory; Woodrow W. Wilson; William B. Wilson; William D. Stephens; Samuel Gompers; Newton D. Baker. Subjects: Mass meeting and local union protests against prosecution of Mooney and Billings; Department of Justice investigation of California state prosecution; Industrial Workers of the World publications; protests against extradition of Alexander Berkman from New York to California; International Workers' Defense League publications.
  - 0559. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Section 1. Previously Restricted Material. 3 pages., 1918; 4 (Reel 1)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings; Charles M. Fickert. Subject: Recall election of San Francisco, California, prosecuting attorney.
  - 0562. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Section 2. 207 pages., 1918-1919; 5 (Reel 1)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings; A. Mitchell Palmer; W. Bourke Cockran. Subjects: Local union and mass meeting protests against prosecution of Mooney and Billings; International Workers' Defense League publications.
  - 0769. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Section 3. 200 pages., 1919-1933; 6 (Reel 1)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings; Roger N. Baldwin; Clarence Senior; Frances Perkins; Homer S. Cummings; Francis Ralston Welsh; Mattie L. Bretland; John Mooney. Subjects: Local union and mass meeting protests against imprisonment of Mooney and Billings; National Mooney-Billings Committee of the American Civil Liberties Union; Socialist party of America; supreme Court of California investigation of convictions of Mooney and Billings; Department of Justice investigation of John Mooney for alleged violations of United states Post Office Department regulations.
  - 0969. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Section 3. Previously Restricted Materials. 10 pages., 1930-1931; 7 (Reel 1)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings; J. Edgar Hoover; Francis Ralston Welsh. Subject: Mooney and Billings Case. For pages omitted after Frame 0978, see end of Reel 1.
  - 0979. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Section 4. 75 pages., 1933-1934; 8 (Reel 1)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings. Subject: Local union and mass meeting protests against imprisonment of Mooney and Billings.
  - 1054. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Section 5. 17 pages., 1933-1934; 9 (Reel 1)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings. Subject: Local union and mass meetings protests against imprisonment of Mooney and Billings.
  - 1071. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Section 6. 61 pages., 1934; 10 (Reel 1)
  - 1132. Industrial Workers of the World Activities in California and the Pacific Northwest. Case File 150139. Section 1. Pages omitted after Frame 0064 of Reel 1. 37 pages., 1914-1915; 11 (Reel 1)
    People: Elizabeth Gurley Flynn; Thomas J. Mooney. Subjects: Industrial Workers of the World publications; International Workers' Defense League publications; insurance company statistics regarding arson and fires in California.
  - 1169. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Section 3. Previously Restricted Material. Pages omitted after Frame 0978 of Reel 1. 10 pages., 1929-1930; 12 (Reel 1)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings; Francis Ralston Welsh; J. Edgar Hoover. Subjects: Mooney and Billings case; Department of Justice investigation of Mooney and Billings case.
- RG 60 - Straight Numerical File (Reel 2)
  - 0001. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Section 7. 98 pages., 1934; 1 (Reel 2)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings; Louis Weinstock; Frank P. Walsh; John F. Finerty; George T. Davis; Upton Sinclair; Roger N. Baldwin. Subjects: Citizen, mass meeting, and local union protests against imprisonment of Mooney and Billings; American Federation of Labor Trades Union Committee for Unemployment Insurance ad Relief; opinions of United states District Court and United States Circuit Court of Appeals judges in Mooney habeas corpus proceedings; Tom Mooney Molders' Defense Committee; International Molders' Union of North America; National Mooney-Billings Committee of the American Civil Liberties Union.
  - 0099. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case file 185354. Section 8. 200 pages., 1934-1935; 2 (Reel 2)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings; John Jenkins; Gardner Jackson; Homer S. Cummings; Rose Wortis; Louis Colman; e. Claude Babcock. Subjects: Citizen, United States congressman, and local union protests against imprisonment of Mooney and Billings; Tom Mooney Defense Committee; International Labor Defense; Federated Moulders' (Metals) Union of Australia; Department of Justice investigation of Mooney and Billings case; Trade Union Unity Council; International Red Aid.
  - 0299. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Section 9. 269 pages., 1935-1937; 3 (Reel 2)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings; Thomas J. Connor; Gunnar Mickelsen. Subjects: Citizen, mass meeting, United States congressman, and local union protests against imprisonment of Mooney and Billings; Department of Justice investigation of Mooney and Billings case; Tom Mooney Molders' Defense Committee; Workers Alliance of America; American Labor party; American Civil Liberties Union; Comintern publications; Farmer-Labor party; 1936 United States presidential elections.
  - 0568. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Section 10. 109 pages., 1937; 4 (Reel 2)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings; John H. Bollens. Subjects: Citizen, mass meeting, and local union protests against imprisonment of Mooney and Billings; American Labor Party; Progressive Women's Council; Civil Rights Federation.
  - 0677. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Section 11. 71 pages., 1937; 5 (Reel 2)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings; Willard Uphaus. Subjects: Citizen, mass meeting, and local union protests against imprisonment of Mooney and Billings; American League against War and Fascism; Religion and Labor Foundation; International Workers Order.
  - 0748. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Section 12. 143 pages., 1937-1962; 6 (Reel 2)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings; J. Edgar Hoover; Martin L. Sweeney. Subjects: Requests for documents relating to Mooney and Billings case; citizen, mass meeting, United States congressman, and local union protests against imprisonment of Mooney and Billings; Workers Alliance of America; Works Progress Administration; International Workers Order; Communist Party of America.
  - 0891. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Protests. Section 1. 194 pages., 1918; 7 (Reel 2)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings. Subjects: Citizen, mass meeting, and local union protests against imprisonment of Mooney and Billings; Socialist party of Kentucky; Socialist party of Indiana.
- RG 60 - Straight Numerical File (Reel 3)
  - 0001. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Protests. Section 2. 341 pages., 1918; 1 (Reel 3)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings; Joseph F. Valentine. Subjects: Citizen, mass meeting, and local union protests against imprisonment of Mooney and Billings; Socialist party of Wisconsin; Socialist party of Ohio; International Molders' Union of North America. For pages omitted after Frame 0075, see reel 3, Frame 1172.
  - 0342. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Special Section 1. 120 pages., 1917; 2 (Reel 3)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings; W.J. Durant. Subjects: Citizen, mass meeting, and local union protests against imprisonment of Mooney and Billings; Socialist party of America.
  - 0462. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Special Section 2. 146 pages., 1917-1918; 3 (Reel 3)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings; John A. Fitch. Subjects: Citizen, mass meeting, and local union protests against imprisonment of Mooney and Billings; National Labor Council; International Workers' Defense League; Tom Mooney Molders' Defense Committee; Socialist party of Mexico.
  - 0608. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Special Section 3. 329 pages., 1918-1938; 4 (Reel 3)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings; Homer S. Cummings; Theodore Debs; Eugene V. Debs; William Mitch; Simon J. Lubin; William Dobson. Subjects: Citizen, mass meeting, United States congressman, and local union protests against imprisonment of Mooney and Billings; International Workers Order; Railroad Employees' Committee for the Release of Thomas J. Mooney; San Francisco Bay Area American Federation of Labor Committee for the Freedom of Mooney and Billings; American Legion; Commission of Immigration and Housing of California.
  - 0937. Industrial Workers of the World - General. Case File 186701. Section 1. 235 pages., 1917-1920; 5 (Reel 3)
    People: Ralph M. Easley; David R. Francis; William English Walling; Carl Hayden; Adolph Germer; Samuel Gompers; Thomas W. Gregory; Woodrow W. Wilson; Leonard Foster. Subjects: Industrial Workers of the World publications; citizen protest against Industrial Workers of the World activities; Great Britain and United States labor union protests against United States treatment of Industrial Workers of the World members; Industrial Workers of the World organization efforts among black Americans; Department of Justice review of espionage convictions and Industrial Workers of the World cases; National Civic Federation; proposed United States recognition of Soviet Russia; United States Post Office Department censorship; criminal prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World leadership; Socialist party of America; Council of National Defense; Employers' Association of the Inland Empire.
  - 1172. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Protests. Section 2. Pages omitted after Frame 0075 of Reel 3. 19 pages., 1918; 6 (Reel 3)
    People: Thomas J. Mooney; Warren K. Billings. Subject: Citizen, mass meeting, and local union protests against imprisonment of Mooney and Billings.
  - 1191. Thomas J. Mooney and Warren K. Billings. Case File 185354. Special Section. Section 1. Pages omitted after Frame 0350 of Reel 3. 15 pages., 1917; 7 (Reel 3)
- RG 60 - Straight Numerical File (Reel 4)
  - 0000. Industrial Workers of the World - General. Case File 186701. Section 2. 23 pages., 1918; 1 (Reel 4)
    People: Roger N. Baldwin; Thomas W. Gregory. Subjects: Requests for documents relating to Department of Justice raid on Industrial Workers of the World Chicago, Illinois, office; citizen protests against Industrial Workers of the World activities; United States Shipping Board investigation of Industrial Workers of the World activities; American Civil Liberties Union; Department of Justice summary of the suppression of Industrial Workers of the World outbreaks.
  - 0023. Industrial Workers of the World - By States. Case File 186701. Section 2. Alaska. 15 pages., 1917-1920; 2 (Reel 4)
    People: Not Available. Subject: Industrial Workers of the World activities in the Alaska Territory
  - 0038. Industrial Workers of the World - General. Case File 186701. Section 2. Previously restricted Materials. 19 pages., 1917-1928; 3 (Reel 4)
    People: J. Edgar Hoover; Thomas W. Gregory. Subjects: Requests for documents relating to Department of Justice prosecutions of Industrial Workers of the World leadership; Labour Defense Council of Great Britain protest against United States suppression of Industrial Workers of the World; citizen protests against alleged Industrial Workers of the World general strike plans.
  - 0057. Industrial Workers of the World - By State. Case File 186701. Section 3. Arizona. 16 pages., 1919-1924; 4 (Reel 4)
    People: A. Mitchell Palmer; Carl Hayden. Subjects: Citizen support for Department of Justice suppression of Industrial Workers of the World in Arizona; American Legion; Industrial Workers of the World activities in Bisbee, Arizona.
  - 0073. Industrial Workers of the World - By State. Case File 186701. Section 4. Arkansas. 7 pages., 1917; 5 (Reel 4)
    People: Not available. Subjects: United States district attorney for the western district of Arkansas request for Secret Service investigation of Industrial Workers of the World activities; Industrial Workers of the World activities in Fort Smith and Mena, Arkansas.
  - 0080. Industrial Workers of the World - By State. Case File 186701. Section 5. California. 150 pages., 1917-1925; 6 (Reel 4)
    People: A Mitchell Palmer; William D. Haywood; William D. Stephens; John W. Preston; Frederick H. Esmond; Thomas W. Gregory; J. Robert O'Connor; Newton D. Baker. Subjects: State and federal suppression of Industrial Workers of the World in California; Department of Justice investigations of Industrial Workers of the World activities; Industrial Workers of the World publications; Industrial Workers of the World General Defense Committee; Industrial Workers of the World songbook; citizen protests against Industrial Workers of the World activities; Sacramento, California, grand jury investigation of Industrial Workers of the World activities; immigrant labor and strikes at mines in Shasta County, California; private detective agencies.
  - 0230. Industrial Workers of the World - By State. Case File 186701. Section 6: Colorado. 8 pages., 1917-1919; 7 (Reel 4)
    People: Not available. Subjects: Department of Justice investigations of Industrial Workers of the World activities in Colorado; Agricultural Workers Industrial Union 1919 convention in Sioux City, Iowa; citizen protests against Industrial Workers of the World activities; Comintern; Department of Justice cooperation with the President's Mediation Commission.
  - 0238. Industrial Workers of the World - By State. Case File 186701. Section 7. Connecticut. 4 pages., 1918; 8 (Reel 4)
    People: Louis C. Fraina. Subject: Formation of the American Red Guard in New York City.
  - 0242. Industrial Workers of the World - By State. Case File 186701. Section 10. Florida. 4 pages., 1919; 9 (Reel 4)
    People: Not available. Subjects: Citizen protests against Industrial Workers of the World activities in Florida; American Legion.
  - 0246. Industrial Workers of the World - By State. Case File 186701. Section 13. Idaho. 80 pages., 1917-1921; 10 (Reel 4)
    People: Alvin M. Owsley; Harry M. Daugherty; Louis F. Post; Thomas W. Gregory; David F. Houston. Subjects: Americanism Commission of the American Legion; citizen protests against Industrial Workers of the World activities in Idaho; Industrial Workers of the World activities in the United States Forest Service; state and Department of Justice suppression of the Industrial Workers of the World; department of Justice investigations of Industrial Workers of the World activities; United States Department of Labor cooperation with Department of Justice; police brutality; protests against mass arrests; United States Department of Agriculture cooperation with department of Justice; Industrial Workers of the World publications; general strikes; state request for Secret Service investigation of Industrial Workers of the World activities.
  - 0326. Industrial Workers of the World - By State. Case File 186701. Section 14. Previously Restricted Materials. Illinois. 61 pages., 1917- 1920; 11 (Reel 4)
    People: J. Edgar Hoover; William J. Burns; Thomas W. Gregory. Subjects: Department of Justice investigation of Industrial Workers of the World activities in Illinois; Department of Justice raids against the Industrial Workers of the World, the Union of Russian Workers, the Communist Labor Party of America, and the Communist Party of America; Non-Partisan League; Department of Justice cooperation with the Department of Justice of Canada; Industrial Workers of the World activities in the United States and Canada; organization of the Industrial Workers of the World Division of the Radical Department of the Bureau of Investigation.
  - 0387. Industrial Workers of the World - By State. Case File 186701. Section 14, Part 1. Illinois. 170 pages., 1917-1920; 12 (Reel 4)
    People: William D. Haywood; George F. Vanderveer; William C. Fitts; Robert Lansing; Thomas W. Gregory; Frank K. Nebeker; Claude R. Porter; John L. Metzen; Kenesaw M. Landis; Adolph Germer. Subjects: Department of Justice investigation of Industrial Workers of the World activities; General Defense Committee of the Industrial Workers of the World; Industrial Workers of the World publications; Railroad Workers Industrial Union; Agricultural Workers Industrial Union; requests for access to Industrial Workers of the World documents held by Judge Kenesaw M. Landis seized in Department of Justice raids; Department of Justice position regarding bail for Industrial Workers of the World defendants; Department of Justice prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World defendants in Illinois; bomb explosion in the United States Post Office Building, Chicago, Illinois; Department of Justice cooperation with United States Department of State; request from the Bulgarian Minister for special privileges for an immigrant Industrial Workers of the World defendant; press coverage of Industrial Workers of the World leadership trial; draft indictment against Adolph Germer, et al., Socialist Party of America, for pro-German matters.
  - 0557. Industrial Workers of the World - By State. Case File 186701. Section 14, Part 2. Illinois. 11 pages., 1922-1924; 13 (Reel 4)
    People: Not available. Subjects: Department of Justice investigation of Industrial Workers of the World activities; citizen protests against Industrial Workers of the World activities in Illinois.
  - 0568. Industrial Workers of the World - By State. Case File 186701. Section 15. Indiana. 19 pages., 1917-1927; 14 (Reel 4)
    People: William J. Donovan. Subjects: Department of Justice investigation of Industrial Workers of the World activities in Indiana; citizen protests against Industrial Workers of the World activities; American Legion; radical activities; strikes in Indiana coal fields.
  - 0587. Industrial Workers of the World - By State. Case File 186701. Section 16. Iowa. 10 pages., 1917-1919; 15 (Reel 4)
    People: Claude R. Porter. Subjects: Department of Justice investigation of Industrial Workers of the World activities in Iowa; 1919 Industrial Workers of the World convention in Sioux City, Iowa; state and federal conspiracy laws.
  - 0597. Industrial Workers of the World - By State. Case File 186701. Section 17. Kansas. 56 pages., 1918-1921; 16 (Reel 4)
    People: Samuel B. Amidon; A. Mitchell Palmer; C. W. Anderson; George F. Vanderveer; Claude R. Porter. Subjects: Department of Justice investigation of Industrial Workers of the World activities in Kansas; Department of Justice prosecution of C. W. Anderson, et al., Wichita, Kansas, Industrial Workers of the World case; Department of Justice cooperation with state authorities; Agricultural Workers Industrial Union; Department of Justice position regarding bail for Industrial Workers of the World defendants.
  - 0653. Industrial Workers of the World - By State. Case File 186701. Section 18. Kentucky. 4 pages., 1917-1918; 17 (Reel 4)
    People: Not available. Subject: Department of Justice investigation of Espionage Act matters in Kentucky.
  - 0657. Industrial Workers of the World - By State. Case File 186701. Section 19. Louisiana. 4 pages., 1920-1922; 18 (Reel 4)
    People: Lucille B. Milner; Harry M. Daugherty. Subjects: Department of Justice investigation of Industrial Workers of the World activities in Louisiana and Arkansas; Department of Justice raids; American Civil Liberties Union.
  - 0661. Industrial Workers of the World - By State. Case File 186701. Section 21. Maine and Maryland. 18 pages., 1918-1924; 19 (Reel 4)